<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine new inventions and profitable experiments necessary to be known of all farmers, and others, that endeavour to procure benefit to themselves, and plentie to the commonwealth.</title>
            <author>Plattes, Gabriel, fl. 1638-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07988</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 82475131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19997.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">82475131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 82475131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">185156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07988)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2255:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine new inventions and profitable experiments necessary to be known of all farmers, and others, that endeavour to procure benefit to themselves, and plentie to the commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>Plattes, Gabriel, fl. 1638-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April. 6. 1640..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Gabriel Plattes by STC (2nd ed.); ms. notes at foot of sheet name "Gabriell Plattes" as the inventor of the devices described.</note>
                  <note>Advertising a new invention for planting corn, beans, and peas.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Massachusetts Historical Society.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Planters (Agricultural machinery) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Agricultural machinery --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Agriculture --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:185156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185156:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185156:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185156:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Certaine new inventions and profitable experiments neceſſary to be known of all Farmers, and others, that endeavour to procure benefit to themſelves, and plentie to the Commonwealth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas many men in this land have found by good experience that Wheat, Beanes, Peaſon, and other corne and ſeeds of divers ſorts, being ſet at conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient depth and diſtance, doe yeeld a wonderfull great encreaſe and benefit, more then by being ſowen the common way, and thereupon many of them have attempted divers wayes for the ſpeedy diſpatching of that worke, but have failed hitherto in their attempts and enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe are to certifie all men, that are deſirous to reape the benefit of ſuch practiſe, that now there is an Engin or Device brought to perfection, which doth excell all practiſes heretofore known for the ſetting of corne, as much as printing excelleth writing for expedition; and is to be ſeene at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Huffes</hi> houſe, at the ſigne of the Claw in the ſtreet called the Bowling alley, neere to Weſtminſter Abbey.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever hath any friends in the counties of <hi>Sommerſet, Gloceſter,</hi> or any other countrey, where they doe generally ſet their Beanes and Peaſe by one at once, he may doe them a friendly office, to informe them of this new invention.</p>
            <p>All Farmers, which have ſuch great Farmes, that they cannot poſſibly ſet their corne, may be there inſtructed in ſeverall experiments for the ordering of Seed-corne, where dung is wanting, that it will yeeld an encreaſe almoſt double to the common way, though it be ſown after the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed manner.</p>
            <p>Alſo they may be inſtructed, how to chuſe and order ſome particular grounds, that the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of them may be clearely recovered at one crop: Whereby any man may gaine as much yearely by a ſmall quantitie of Land, as others get by thrice as much uſed the ordinary way.</p>
            <p>Alſo they may be inſtructed in many notable experiments, for the improving of divers ſort of Land, whereby they may get a good advantage to themſelves, and procure an ineſtimable benefit to the Common-wealth, being generally practiſed.</p>
            <p>As alſo how to convert to the beſt uſes, divers things, which have in all ages heretofore been fondly caſt away, whereof one loade will be as effectuall for the enriching of barren land, as twentie loades of dung.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that love themſelves or the common good, are invited and deſired to learn the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this new invention for the expeditious ſetting of corne, againſt the time of dearth and ſcarcitie; For, when corne is at an high price, any Farmer that uſually ſoweth twentie quarters of corne yearely, may ſet the ſame Land with three quarters, and may have a farre better encreaſe at harveſt, then if he had ſowen the whole twentie quarters, ſo that he may ſell ſeventeene quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſeed corne, put fortie or fiftie pounds in his purſe, though he pay his workmen at an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate, then they have for their common employments, by which means he ſhall not want work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: and befides the corne thus ſpared, being uſed for bread-corne, in the ſame countrey, will keepe that wealth at home, which muſt otherwiſe have been exhauſted in buying corne brought from forrein parts. So that this skill well learned before hand, may be a better prevention againſt dearth, then all Store-houſes and proviſions heretofore deviſed.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever ſhall procure dearth or ſcarcitie the people will curſe them, but bleſſing ſhall be upon the heads of thoſe that endeavour to cauſe plentie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>April. 6. 1640.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Thoſe that dwell in any countrey farre diſtant, and deſire to reape the benefit of theſe new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, may joyne many together in the charge, and ſend a capacious man to the place above appointed, who ſhall preſently receive full ſatisfaction, concerning the truth, and certaintie of all the experiments above menrioned.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>
               <add>Gabriell Plattes (that made the 2 Bookes I sent yo<hi rend="sup">u</hi>.) hath a Booke readie for the Proſes of theſe experiments, I have read it over &amp; ſeene his Engine but—more of that hereafter; if yo<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thinke fitt./</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
